Guide to the Montana Legislative Assembly (30th: 1947) records 1945-1947
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Montana Legislative Assembly (30th: 1947) records
1945-1947
LR 30 (51:6-2)
Montana. Legislative Assembly.
.8 linear feet of shelf space
Collection contains records (1945-1947) of the Montana 30th Legislative Assembly including minutes of a Special Joint Committee to Investigate the Highway Commission; a report of a House Special Committee to Investigate the Liquor Control Board; minutes of House and Senate standing committees; House and Senate bills, resolutions, memorials, joint resolutions and status sheets.
The Montana State Legislature is made up of two chambers, the Senate and the House of Representatives. The Constitution of Montana limits the size of the Senate to no fewer than 40 and no more than 50 members and the size of the House of Representatives to no fewer than 80 and no more than 100 members. Each house is responsible for choosing its officers, creating committees and establishing its own rules. The Montana Legislature meets for 90 days every odd numbered year, beginning the first Monday in January, or the following Wednesday if the first Monday is New Years Day. The first State Legislature convened on November 23, 1889, fifteen days after Montana became a state. Each following Legislature has been numbered sequentially.
The 30th Montana Legislature met from January 6th to March 6th, 1947. The leaders of the Senate were Ernest Eaton (R-President), and Tom Burke (R-President Pro Tempore and Majority Leader). The leaders of the House were Charles Scofield (R-Speaker), Dean Chaffin (R-Speaker Pro Tempore), and Ory Armstrong (R-Majority Leader).
Sources:The Constitution of the State of Montana as adopted by the Constitutional Convention March 22, 1972, and as ratified by the people, June 6, 1972, referendum no. 68, "A GUIDE TO THE MONTANA LEGISLATURE," The Montana Legislature,; “Montana Legislative Leadership 1889 – Present”.
This collection includes the minutes of a Special Joint Committee to Investigate the Highway Commission; a report of a House Special Committee to Investigate the Liquor Control Board; a summary of "Educational Legislation" from the House Standing Committee; minutes of House and Senate standing committees; House and Senate bills, resolutions, memorials (re James N. Doherty), joint resolutions and status sheets. The collection also contains miscellany material including exhibits regarding Post War Planning and Construction commission; list of bills handled by Senate Finance and Claims Committee; and a "Summary of Changes in Juvenile Delinquency Law which will be effected by the Enactment of SB 123"
The collection is organized into four series, House and Senate Joint Committees, House of Representatives, Senate, and Miscellany (arranged alphabetically).
The series House and Senate Joint Committees is organized into two subseries, Joint Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically), and Special Joint Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically).
The series House of Representatives is organized into nine subseries, House Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically), House Bills (arranged numerically), House Standing Committee Reports (arranged alphabetically), House Special Committee Reports (arranged alphabetically), House Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically), Status Sheets of House Bills (arranged chronologically), House Journal (arranged chronologically), House Memorial Resolutions (arranged numerically), and House Joint Memorials (arranged numerically).
The series Senate is organized into seven subseries, Senate Standing Committee Minutes (arranged alphabetically), Senate Bills (arranged numerically), Senate Standing Committee Reports (arranged alphabetically), Senate Joint Resolutions (arranged numerically), Status Sheets of Senate Bills (arranged chronologically), Senate Journal (arranged chronologically), and Senate Joint Memorials (arranged numerically).
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Bills, Legislative--Montana.; Legislative bodies--Committees--Montana.; Montana. Legislative Assembly--investigations
Montana--Politics and government.
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
- House and Senate Joint Committees
  - Joint Committee Minutes
    - House Appropriations for Greater University; Senate Finance and Claims on Education (includes reports on university and colleges), January 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Special Joint Committee Minutes
    - House and Senate committee to investigate the Highways Commission (joint committee on Highway Investigation), February 5, March 4, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
- House of Representatives
  - House Standing Committee Minutes
    - Appropriations (includes deficiency claims, status sheets and summary of bills), January 7-February 27, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
    - Federal Relations, January 15-February 26, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
    - Irrigation and Water Rights, February 4, 11, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - Judiciary, January 14-February 15, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
    - Mines and Mining, February 20, 25, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
    - Public Utilities and State Commissions, January 15, 21, February 24, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
    - State Boards and Offices (includes resolutions from Public Health League of Montana, Hospital Association of Montana, Helena Fraternal Order of Elks opposing H.B. 62), January 16-February 27, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
    - State Institutions, Public Buildings and Grounds, January 16, February 5-18, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - House Bills
    - Bill nos. 1-98, 101-440, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 11-14)
  - House Standing Committee Reports
    - Education (includes "Summary of Educational Legislation"), 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - House Special Committee Reports
    - Liquor Control subcommittee to investigate activities and business administration of Liquor Control, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - House Joint Resolutions
    - Bill no. 1, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
  - Status Sheets of House Bills
    - 57th-60th Legislative Days, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
  - House Journal
    - 57th-59th Legislative Days, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
  - House Memorial Resolutions
    - re James N. Doherty, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
  - House Joint Memorials
    - Bill nos. 1-12, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 21)
- Senate
  - Senate Standing Committee Minutes
    - Business Administration, February 6-26, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 22)
    - Counties and Towns, January 28, 30, February 3-26, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 23)
    - Dairies and Dairying, February 25, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 24)
    - Elections and Privileges, January 21, February 3-21, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 25)
    - Judicial Districts, February 5, 7, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 26)
    - Labor and Capital, February 11-15, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 27)
    - Military Affairs, January 28, 30, February 3-21, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 28)
    - Mines and Mining, January 31, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
    - Oils and Leases, January 23 - February 28, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
    - Public Buildings, February 24, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
    - Public Health and Sanitation, January 21-March 4, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
    - Public Lands, January 20-February 22, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
    - Railroads and Transportation, February 3, 25, 27, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
    - State and County Economics, January 26-February 15, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
    - Stockgrowing and Grazing, January 22- March 3, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 8)
    - Taxation (includes hearing on HB 251 re slot machines), January 28- February 27, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 9)
    - Water, Conservation, and Flood Control, January 20- February 27, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
  - Senate Bills
    - Nos. 1-162, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - Senate Standing Committee Reports
    - Education (includes summary of principal education measures), 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - Senate Joint Resolutions
    - No. 1, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
  - Status Sheets of Senate Bills
    - 57th-59th legislative days, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
  - Senate Journal
    - 57th-59th legislative records, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 15)
  - Senate Joint Memorials
    - Nos. 1-17, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 16)
- Miscellany
  - Exhibits (re Post War Planning and Construction Commission; University Appropriations), 1945, 1946 (Box-folder 2 / 17)
  - General fund estimate, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 18)
  - List of bills handled by Senate Finance and Claims Committee, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 19)
  - List of members of the Senate Horticulture Committee, 1947 (Box-folder 2 / 20)
  - "Montana Arson Law Comparison of Present Montana Arson Statutes with Proposed Bill" (re SB 28), undated (Box-folder 2 / 21)
  - "Proposed Montana Small Loan Act with Explanations", 1946 (Box-folder 2 / 22)
  - "Summary of Changes in Juvenile Delinquency Law which will be effected by the Enactment of SB 123", undated (Box-folder 2 / 23)